Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
- Manuscripts
  - Chronological
    - Lafayette to General Waine (Wayne) - Gives him the news from the South, 1781, July 25; Photostat 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lafayette to Governor Nelson - Referring to Colonel Gist, 1781, July 26; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - George III - signed also by Lord North and Lord Palmerton - Pay Warrant for supplies for the Army serving in the Carolinas, 1781, July 26 (Ovflat 30)
    - Lafayette to Washington - Reports on the movements of the British Army and news of their fleets, 1781, July 26; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to Congress - Enclosing copy of letter to Washington, 1781, July 26; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to Governor Nelson - Concerning Capt. Segond, 1781, July 27; Photostat 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
      "NOTE - The covering sheet is addressed to Gov. Nelson, although the letter is marked for Gov. Lee (MD) evidently a mistake."
    - Lafayette to the Governor of Virginia - General Weedon's movements, 1781, July 27; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to General Weedon - Some 3000 of the enemy have embarked at Hampton Road, supposedly for New York, 1781, July 27; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to Governor Nelson - A plan for drawing money, 1781, July 29; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to Governor Nelson - Suggestions about reinforcing General Greene - some surmises about the French fleet, 1781, July 29; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to Washington - The position of Wayne's men, Muhlenberg's command and the soldiers under Weedon. A postscript reads "An Hessian deserter just arrived says he understood from his comrades that the whole 800 Germans was to embark, but your Excellency knows no great dependence is to be put on those people", 1781, July 30; Photostat 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Washington to Lafayette - "I take your private letter of the 20th in the light which you wish it, that of an unreserved communication from one friend to another, and I should be wanting in candor were I not to expose my sentiments to you in as free a manner" - Washington then proceeds to inform him that his wish to be active is about to be fulfilled as they have already made changes in the Weatherfield plan of campaign, 1781, July 30; Photostat 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Commander James Barron to ? - The British Fleet weighed this morning from Cape Henry and stood up in the Bay - it is certain that they are bound for Baltimore, 1781, July 31; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - News from the North - both the French and American Armies are at Dobbs Ferry - the enemy tremble at the prospect of a siege of New York, 1781, July 31; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lafayette to Washington - Intimates that Lafayette had a secret agent working as a servant in the immediate entourage of Lord Cornwallis, 1781, July 31; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Appeal of de la Mothe (a French spy) to King of England, 1781, July; ADS (Box 1, Folder 36)
      "NOTE - It was of no avail as he was executed in London on July 27, 1781."
    - Lafayette to President McKean, of Congress - Information of the Cornwallis movements at Portsmouth and enclosing letters from James Barron and Colonel Parker, 1781, August 1; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to General Washington - Mentions Macpherson and his distinguished services, 1781, August 1; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes photostat of July 24 letter enclosed
    - Lafayette to General Greene - A Commissary of military stores just arrived from the Board of War, 1781, August 4; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - I will send you copies of my correspondence with Lord Cornwallis - his politeness to me and the Troops in this state has been uninterrupted, but his commissaries, unless he has interposed, have been cunning as usual, 1781, August 4; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - Expressing sympathy for the British prisoners of war and authorizing the use of Government money in their relief, 1781, August 5; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Col. Davie - He is short of arms and ammunition - The militia cannot be persuaded into a care of their arms, 1781, August 6; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Brigadier General Mordecai Gist - Orders about new State levies, 1781, August 6; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette - "The negotiations between England and Holland thro' a Russian mediation is lately broke up and every idea of a partial peace given up", 1781, August 6; ADS (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Congress - It gets its first news that Cornwallis has begun to fortify Yorktown, 1781, August 6; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Washington - Advising that cornwallis and his troops have sailed up York River - he describes the town of York (Yorktown) as surrounded by the river and a morass "but there is a commanding hill which if occupied would much extend their works", 1781, August 6; Photostat 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to General Weedon - The enemy are fortifying at York, 1781, August 6; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - Suggesting certain preparations for the coming campaign, 1781, August 7; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Brig. Gen. Roger Newberry to Col. Howell Woodbridge of the 6th Connecticut Militia - Official call for men and baggage wagons, 1781, August 9; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Secretarial extract from General Wayne's letter to Lafayette, 1781, August 9; ADS (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Also includes photostat copy, 2 p.
    - Major John Habersham to Lafayette - He and his fellow Officers complain of the treatment by the British at the time of the Capitulation of Charleston, 1781, August 10; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Washington - Confidential report of a sharp disagreement between the Virginia troops and those of Penna. He writes "I perceive the seeds of a future dispute between the States", 1781, August 11; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - "Your Lieutenant (Lafayette) is become so wise a man that his whole 'sistim' is bent to preservation." - Cornwallis is prudent and cautious, 1781, August 12; Photostat 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Greene - A long letter on the situation. Evidently Greene has asked for service of McHenry and Lafayette discusses him rather intimately, 1781, August 12; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - "I readily confess that the sums of 'monney' that have been drawn are extravagant, as they are proportionate to the price extorted for every article and the lamentable depreciacion of 'monney'", 1781, August 12; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - About stores, 1781, August 12; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - About the British fortifications at Yorktown adn Gloucester, 1781, August 13; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Includes typed title on scrapbook page
    - Lafayette to Col. Davie - Again stressing the need of equipment, 1781, August 13; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Colonel Davie - Asking for the impressment of sufficient "waggons" for bringing up provisions, 1781, August 14; ADS (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Congress - Enclosing a letter from Mr. Jefferson. "From a sense of that gentleman's ability I cannot help presuming to observe that the shortness of time has been, is apparent, his only objection to the acceptance of the apointment - ". Lafayette is surprised that the British have not been more active in their fortification work at Yorktown, 1781, August 14; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 2)
      "NOTE - It would be interesting to know what appointment was being considered by Jefferson. In June of that year he had been succeeded as Governor of Virginia by Nelson, and some of his associates in the government of that state were trying to stir up trouble for him because the British had been so successful in their raids. It is hardly likely that Jefferson could have done anything to prevent these, at least Lafayette did not think so. He had such a high respect for Mr. Jefferson that their friendship continued for many years after the war."
    - Lafayette to Charles Thompson, Secretary of Congress - Acknowledging his letter to the effect that Samuel Huntington has resigned the Presidency and that Thomas McKean is elected to succeed him, 1781, August 15; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Washington to Lafayette - The happy news that de Grasse has sailed from the West Indies and is headed for the Chesapeake - Orders for Lafayette to take such a position as will prevent the retreat of Cornwallis through North Carolina, 1781, August 15; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson (?) - He has sent a detachment to the "Gloster" side to restrain the enemy's raiding party, 1781, August 16; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Stating that General du Portail is starting South with instructions for Lafayette, 1781, August 17; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to General Weedon - The enemy at York are joining Cornwallis at Gloucester, 1781, August 18; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - On his lack of "waggons", 1781, August 19; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - Judging from Cornwallis' movements it would appear that he is on the point of becoming active, 1781, August 20; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - About money matters - with a notation concerning some French privateer vessel, 1781, August 20; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette to Washington - "The greater part of the enemy is at York, which they do not as yet fortify but are very busy upon Gloster Neck, where they have a pretty large corps...they have at York a 44 gun ship...a small garrison at Portsmouth...should they intend to evacuate they are proceeding with amazing slowness", 1781, August 21; Photostat 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Important instructions and a notation that he is enclosing an unsealed letter which is to be conveyed to de Grasse, 1781, August 21; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Thomas McKean, President of Congress - Reports that both sides are marking time, 1781, August 21; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
      "NOTE - McKean was the only member of Congress to serve continuously from 1774 through to the Peace of 1783."
    - Lafayette to Capt. Rudolph - Will write to Board of War recommending equipment for his men - "I will send you a letter to Gov. Lee on the subject of permitting you to recruit in Maryland. But can you recruit without money?", 1781, August 22; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      "NOTE - The body of the letter is in the handwriting of Lafayette's military secretary, Col. North."
    - Lafayette to Congress, 1781, August 23; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Sending Major Gibbs to replace Major Galvan, 1781, August 24; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - Can he issue warrants for certain officers taken in the surrender of Charleston, 1781, August 25; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Col. Davie, 1781, August 25; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - Sad condition of his troops - Ineffectiveness of militia - "And the poor Continentals that will soon be our only dependence, falling for want of spirits and flour...should it be known to Lord Cornwallis he may ruin us at one stroke...", 1781, August 26; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - No plans have yet been received from General Washington, 1781, August 27; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Secretarial copy of letter from Lafayette to Brig. General Jones, 1781, August 27; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Washington to Lafayette - "The whole force will leave here and move on to Trenton..." They are on their way to the head of Elk and intelligence is asked of the best place in Virginia for the debarkation of the French and American troops, 1781, August 27; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Baron Viomenil to General Washington - Concerning protection for the bakeries at Chatham, NJ, 1781, August 28; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Col. Davie, 1781, August 30; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - Seven page letter discussing the probable plans of Cornwallis and giving some idea of Lafayette's future movements, 1781, August 30; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 3)
      "It is likely that Lafayette's military secretary North wrote the letter to which is appended a postscript in Lafayette's own hand."
    - Lafayette to Col. Taylor - A fleet has been sighted, but it is not yet known to be British or French, 1781, August 31; ADS (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Colonel Parker - Return of cannon left in Portsmouth by the enemy, 1781, August; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lafayette to General Weedon - News of the arrival of Admiral de Grasse in the Bay with 28 battle ships, 1781, September 1; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Washington to Lafayette - News of the British fleet--and of the French and American troops that are marching south, 1781, September 1; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - "I am happy to inform you that Commander de Grasse is safely arrived in the Bay", 1781, September 2; Photostat 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Nelson - The French troops are landing at Jamestown, 1781, September 2; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Washington to Lafayette - A long acocunt of the preparations of the coming campaign - "But, my dear Marquis, I am distressed beyond expression to know what has become of Count de Grasse... and also solicitous for the Count de Barras who was to have sailed from Rhode Island", 1781, September 2; Photostat 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Colonel William Stephens Smith to Morgan Lewis at Albany - Order to pay Robert Morris £50 Pennsylvania currency equal to 133 1/3 hard Spanish dollars, 1781, September 4; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson - "The Count de Grasse writes me that his fleet is suffering for fresh water", 1781, September 5; ADS (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Gov. Nelson on hospital supplies, 1781, September 6; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Expressing his pleasure at learning of the arrival of de Grasse and his fleet, 1781, September 7; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Colonel Taylor - "I have ordered the Militia to rendevouz at the Gloster Camp", 1781, September 8; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Washington - News of a naval engagement off the "Capes", 1781, September 8; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Washington - Tells of the "Surprisingly speeding landing" of the French troops under St. Simon and the junction of the French and the Americans at Williamsburg, 1781, September 10; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to General Weedon - Asks him to take command of 1000 militia at Gloucester - the French fleet needs flour, 1781, September 11; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Governor Nelson - Suggesting that as neither the French nor American troops have any flour, the Governor might seize some of the private vessels - "In the winter of 1780, when the G.A. was on the point of disbanding for want of provisions, a large and instant supply was obtained by the seizure of private property", 1781, September 11; Photostat 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General Heath requests the Pastor of the Reformed Church of Hackensack to do secret service work for the American Cause, 1781, September 24; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      "In the catalogue of Walter R. Benjamin this item was noted as being addressed to Rev. Theodorick Romeyn. When I bought the letter I asked Mr. Benjamin if he was sure of the "Theodorick" as I happen to know that the Pastor of the Dutch Church was "Dierck" Romeyn. (The letter carries no first name.) He replied that this letter came out of his own family papers - that the addressee was a cousin of his great grandfather, Benjamin Romeyn, and that "Dierck" is the Dutch form of "Theodorick," and Mr. Benjamin signed his letter "W. Romeyn Benjamin.""
    - Administration charges against the estate of Daniel Phelps - allowed by Oliver W., Judge, 1781, September 24; ADS (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Quartermaster General Timothy Pickering to General Lincoln - about supplies for Lafayette, 1781, September 25; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to Washington - "Col. Scammel is taken", 1781, September 30; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - "Your Country has been saved by a Virginian and the Southern States have been retrieved by a Yankee", 1781, October 6; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to Washington - His formal report on the action at Yorktown, 1781, October 16; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Baron Viomenil to ? - On military movements, 1781, October 16; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Listed as "september 16" in binder
    - Formal report on the Yorktown surrender, made by Cornwallis to Sir Henry Clinton, 1781, October 20; Photostat 15 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
      "The original Cornwallis letter is owned by William L. Clements, Esq."
    - Louis XVI to Monsieur de Querelles - Instructions for a Te Deum for the Dauphin, 1781, October 22; ADS (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Also includes typed title on scrapbook page
    - Lord Cornwallis - His Official parole, 1781, October 28; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to Governor Nelson - Letter of farewell, 1781, October 31; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Washington to Lafayette - Refers to the British as still in the Carolinas and to the departure of de Grasse - "It follows that as certain as that night succeeds day that without a decisive naval force we can do nothing definitive - with one, everything honorable and glorious", 1781, November 15; Photostat 5 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to General Greene - He regrets that the "old Admiral" did not agree to his suggestion of an attack on Wilmington - he will return to France where he will scheme a campaign against Charleston - "I will return next Spring", 1781, November 22; Photostat 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to Congress - Indicates that he did not think the Yorktown capitulation had ended the war and suggests that his return to France could be serviceable for the "next campaign", 1781, November 22; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Increase Sumner to Honorable Samuel Holten - Pleads for bailment of Benjamin Shaw who is in jail for passing counterfeit Continental money, 1781, November 22; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Statement of the account between Lafayette and Leray de Chaumont, Intendant of the French Army, 1781, November 23; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to Congress - Thanking them for the Resolution passed in his favor - "With unspeakable pleasure I shall transmit the Resolve of Congress to the brave and virtuous troops whom it has been my happiness to command", 1781, November 25; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to Washington - Arranging for a code, 1781, November 29; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - John Dickinson to the Secretary of War - He understands that the Commander-in-Chief has sent from York in Virginia, supplies of "cloathes" for the Southern Army - what action should Delaware take, if any, 1781, December 3; ADS (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Commissaire Ordonnateur des Guerres - Regarding the decoration of M. Rousset and M. Clement de Diet (?), 1781, December 5; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Richard Starke to his brother Commander Starke of H.M.S. "Maria" - Tells of the effect on the British of the Cornwallis surrender - "Admirals Graves and Hook are on bad terms and recriminate each other with respect to the action off the Capes of Virginia on Sept. 5th", 1781, December 11; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General Weedon - Payment for horse forage, 1781, December 11; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Baron d'Esebeck (one of the Deux Ponts who served with Rochambeau) - He remained in Virginia and writes of the interesting country life of the gentry, 1781, December 12; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lafayette to Congress - His farewell respects - "I dare flatter myself they will accept of this homage of an affectionate heart", 1781, December 23; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Rochambeau to Washington - Has information to the effect that the British had evacuated Wilmington, 1781, December 24; Photostat 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Captain Coit - Inquires about certain papers lost when the British raided New London in December 1781, 1782, January 3; ADS (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ferdinand, Duke of Parma to "Monsieur le Comte" - Wishing him a happy New Year, 1782, January 4; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Washington to Lafayette - "I have remained at this place ever since you left it and am happy in having discovered the best disposition imaginable in Congress to prepare vigorously for another campaign", 1782, January 4; Photostat 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lafayette to Congress - He has safely reached France - is much indebted to Capt. John Barry of the "Alliance" and "However happy I feel in the prospect to be in three days with my family and friends, I do not for an instant lose another prospect which is also very dear to my heart, that of being in a short time returned to America", 1782, January 18; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General Alexander McDougall to Colonel Hughes - Desires him to report on any expenses that should be charged against him or Mrs. McDougall, 1782, January 22; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Robert Morris to John Brown - "I am well pleased that the 'Alliance' got away without detaining the Marquis too long and I am rather pleased that no force was used to compel the people from the 'Deane' to the other, although it is very obvious that if such a power cannot be exercised, our Navy will never be on the footing it ought", 1782, January 23; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lafayette to Congress - "He (Franklin) was pleased to accept of my services as a political aide de camp...the reception I have met with is the more flattering to me as it evinces nothing weighs so much with the Nation and her Soverign, as an ardent zeal for the cause of America and honorable testimony of her confidence", 1782, January 29; Photostat 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General Joseph Palmer to John Hancock - Enclosing receipts, 1782, February 19; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Robert Morris to John Taylor - Congress has no money to pay interest on public debt, but Massachusetts may soon pass Import Law, as suggested by Congress the year before and Rhode Island and Maryland may follow. This would complete the roll of States. Morris hopes the creditors will get relief, 1782, February 25; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lafayette to Count de Jarnac - Concerning a British prisoner in the U.S., 1782, March 6; Photostat (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Comte de Custine of the Reg. Saintonge - He explained, at the request of Marquis de Segur, the "Affair of March 1781" - How he established discipline and of the opposition by Deforets to the punishments given, 1782, March 11; ADS 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes typed title and explanation on scrapbook page